A Finding Aid to the San Francisco Women Artists Records, 1925-1999, in the Archives of American Art AAA.sanfrawa
Archives of American Art
San Francisco Women Artists records
1925-1999
AAA.sanfrawa
Archives of American Art
15.3 Linear feet
The San Francisco Women Artists records measure 15.3 linear feet, date from 1925 to 1999, and include administrative records, correspondence, membership files, exhibition files, inventory records, printed material, twenty scrapbooks, photographs, and eight photograph albums.
San Francisco Women Artists.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 8 series:
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1925-circa 1998 (6.3 linear feet; Boxes 1-6, 15)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1931-1998 (0.7 linear feet; Boxes 6-7)
Series 3: Membership Files, 1925-circa 1998 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 7-8)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1947-circa 1998 (0.7 linear feet; Boxes 8-9)
Series 5: Inventory Records, circa 1974-circa 1985 (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 9-10)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1926-1999 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 10-11, 16)
Series 7: Scrapbooks, 1925-circa 1990s (2.7 linear feet; Boxes 11-13, 15)
Series 8: Photographs 1970-circa 1990s (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 13-14, 16)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical/Historical note
San Francisco Women Artists (SFWA) is one of California's oldest arts organizations, dating its founding to 1887 as the Sketch Club. At that time, members met monthly to share and critique one another's work and to travel together on sketching trips. After the great earthquake in 1906 destroyed the club's headquarters, the group floundered and reorganized and merged with other organizations that also included men. By 1925, however, a core group of women broke away and formed the San Francisco Society of Women Artists. The SFWA's founding mission was "... the study and furtherance of all interests common to the arts both graphic and plastic … and to support causes neglected by other art organizations in the Bay Area.” Early members include Alice B. Chittenden, Helen Hyde, Matilda Lotz, Clara Taggart McChesney, M. Evelyn McCormick, Dora Williams, and Eva Almond Withrow. Other members included Marcelle Labaudt, Dorr Bothwell, Claire Falkenstein, Ruth Asawa, Nell Sinton, Imogen Cunningham, Eleanor Dickenson, Jo Hansen, Emmy Lou Packard, Eleanore Rappe, Ruth Armer, Barbara Spring, Beth Van Hoesen and Dorothy Winslade.
The Society held its first exhibition in 1926. In 1932, Frida Kahlo’s painting, Frieda and Diego Rivera, was shown at the “Sixth Annual Exhibition of the San Francisco Society of Women Artists” and was the first public showing of Kahlo’s work. In 1946 the organization shortened its name to the San Francisco Women Artists.
In 1976 the SFWA and exective director Marcelle Labaudt were commended in a Senate Resolution for “outstanding contributions to the cultural enhancement of the City of San Francisco.” In 1983 the SFWA procured a gallery at 451 Hayes Street, which provided exhibition space for members, as well as an art rental program. In 1985 the gallery moved to 370 Hayes Street. The SFWA celebrated its centennial in 1994 with an exhibition including work of many past members.
This organization continues to host monthly themed juried shows and is dedicated to encouraging and promoting the work of women artists.
Scope and Contents note
The San Francisco Women Artists records measure 15.3 linear feet and date from 1925 to 1999. The activities of the SFWA are documented through administrative records, correspondence, membership files, exhibition files, inventory records, printed material, twenty scrapbooks, photographs, and eight photograph albums.
Administrative records include daily journals and publicity materials, historical materials and founding documents, meeting minutes and agendas, artist council and committee meetings, and member and patron surveys. Also found within administrative records are materials on Marcelle Labaudt, SFWA Executive Secretary then Executive Director for many years, including original film footage and sound recordings for a career retrospective film project. Correspondence is with potential donors and patrons, board members, members, and artists. Membership files contain ledgers of paid memberships, lists of dropped members, membership applications and rosters, membership biographies, renewals and statistics, and membership directories.
Exhibition files contain price lists and display placards, slides and photographs, and printed materials relating to shows and exhibitions presented by various SFWA members and cooperating organizations, including the San Francisco Art Institute. Shows include “Celebration of International Women” (1991), “The Paintings of Dorothy Windslade” (1994), annual juried SFWA shows and emerging artists exhibitions (1947-circa 1994), “Art of Susan A. Whitney Exhibit and Silent Auction” (1997), and “Hands and Heart, the Art of Healing” (1997), among others.
Inventory records contain artist inventory cards noting various artwork and exhibitions. Printed material includes books, SFWA bulletins, SFWA calendars, clippings, and exhibition printed materials, such as announcements, brochures, and catalogs. Twenty scrapbooks document the SFWA through clippings, exhibition documentation, photographs, biographies, and annotations. Eight photograph albums depict exhibitions and shows, artwork and artists. Also found within photographs are slides, negatives, and loose photographs depicting works of art, gallery and receptions, and meetings.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Pam Foley, president of the San Francisco Women Artists donated the records in 1999.
Labaudt, Marcelle, 1892-1987; San Francisco Art Institute; Whitney, Susan A.; Windslade, Dorothy; Art--Societies, etc.--California--San Francisco; Motion pictures (visual works); Photograph albums; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Women artists--California--San Francisco
- Administrative Records, 1925-circa 1998; Series 1; 6.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-6, 15
  Scope and Contents note
  Administrative records include a wide variety of materials documenting the organization's general administrative, financial, and operating affairs; founding and history; events; board, council, and committee activities;and membership information. Also found are biographical materials on Marcelle Labaudt, long-time member and and executive director of the SFWA. Within the files concerning Labault is material documenting a film project about Labault by Marlana Beckman, which includes film and sound recordings.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged by functions, activities, and subjects.
  - Annual Reports, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artist Council, circa 1992-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - Committees, 1992-circa 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Daily Journal, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Daily Journal, circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Daily Journal, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Daily Journal, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Daily Journal, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Directories, 1949-1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Events, "Fun For Funds", circa 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Events, Help Save Our Gallery, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Events, International Women's Day Luncheon, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Events, San Francisco Annual Arts Festival, circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Events, SFWA and KQED Channel 9 Pledge Night, circa 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Financial Files, Income and Expense Reports, circa 1992-1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Financial Files, Marketing and Budget Plans, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Financial Files, Sales Tax Reports, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Financial Files, Treasurer's Reports, 1960-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22-27)
  - Founding Documents, Constitution, By-Laws, and Articles of Incorporation, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 28-31)
  - Gallery Comment Book, circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Gallery Operations (Box 1)
    - Bell, Curtis and Snider Fine Art Planning Proposal, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Brochures, New, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Gallery Leasing and Usage Contract, 1976-1985 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Guest Book, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Gallery Operations (Box 2)
    - Job Search, Gallery Manager, circa 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Outside Receptions and Gallery Rentals, circa 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Ordering Guest Books, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Receiving Book, Exhibitions, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Supplies, Ordering Invitations, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Supplies, Short-Run Labels, Inc., circa 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Supplies, Stationery, circa 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Website, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General Administrative Records, 1925-1951 (Box 2, Folder 10-27)
  - General Administrative Records, circa 1946-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1-24)
  - General Administrative Records, circa 1975-circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 1-25)
  - General Administrative Records, circa 1990-circa 1994 (Box 5, Folder 1-10)
  - Hayes Valley Merchants Association, circa 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
  - History of SFWA (Box 5)
    - Biographies, circa 1990-circa 1998 (Box 5, Folder 14-18)
    - Booklet, circa 1997 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Copies of Clippings, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Dorr Bothwell Lecture, "SF Art Institute Lecture", circa 1996; 2 cassette tapes Includes paper notes and additional description. (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - General History of SFWA, circa 1930-1996 (Box 5, Folder 22-24)
    - Obituaries, circa 1991-1998 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Radio Program, "KPFA-FM Heritage Program" Sound Recording, circa 1989; 1 cassette tapes Descriptive note included. (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Radio Program, "SFWA on KALW", circa 1998; 1 cassette tapes (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Video Recording, "Art and Music: Everybody's Angels", circa 1998; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Descriptive note included. (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Marcelle Labaudt (Box 6)
    - "Marcelle Labaudt Film" Materials, Information, circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "Marcelle Labaudt Film" Materials, Film Recordings, circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Film recordings housed in Box 15.
    - "Marcell Labaudt Film" Materials, Sound Recordings, circa 1980s; 6 sound tape reels (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
      Oversized film material located in Box 15.
    - "Marcelle Labaudt Film" Materials, Sound Recordings, circa 1980s; 3 cassette tapes (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Cassette tapes may be copies of sound reels.
    - Printed Material, 1976-1981 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Loose Clippings Scrapbook, circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Slides, Carousel I: "Attic Reception, Labaudt Slides and Festivals", circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Slides, Carousel II: "Lucien Labaudt's Reception Anniversary", circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Slides, Carousel III: "Lucien Show, Etc.", circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Marcelle Labaudt Scholarship Fund, circa 1987-1996 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Meetings, circa 1992-1998 (Box 6, Folder 13-16)
  - Miscellaneous Research, Women Artists, circa 1990s (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Officers and Directors, circa 1945-circa 1990s (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
  - Presidents' Talks, 1992-1998 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Publicity, circa 1951-circa 1994 (Box 6, Folder 21-24)
  - Rental Gallery of SFWA, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Surveys and Questionnaires, 1990-1998 (Box 6, Folder 26-31)
  - Oversized "Marcelle Labaudt Film" Materials, Film Recordings, circa 1980s; 2 Film reels 16 mm (Box 15)
- Correspondence, 1931-1998; Series 2; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  Correspondence is with donors and patrons, artists and members, board members, SFWA President Stefanie Steinberg, and others. Additional correspondence is found in Series 1.
  - Potential Donors and Patrons, circa 1996 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Stefanie Steinberg, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - General, 1931-1932 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - General, 1931-1997 (Box 7, Folder 1-10)
  - Donor Thank You Notes, 1993-1998 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
  - to Irene Pattinson, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - to the Board from Members, circa 1995-1997 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Membership Files, 1925-circa 1998; Series 3; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 7-8
  Membership files include rosters, renewals, directories, statistics, and applications, dropped members lists, printed membership applications, a letter for overdue membership, as well as two ledgers of paid memberships.
  - Dropped Members, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Ledger, Paid Memberships, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Ledger, Paid Memberships, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Letter for Overdue Membership, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Membership Applications, circa 1979-circa 1986 (Box 7, Folder 19-28)
  - Membership Applications, circa 1984-1998 (Box 8, Folder 1-9)
  - Member Biographies, circa 1998 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
  - Membership Directory, 1975-1997 (Box 8, Folder 12-14)
  - Membership Renewals, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Membership Rosters, 1925-1998 (Box 8, Folder 16-28)
  - Membership Statistics, 1947-1949 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Old Membership Applications, circa 1992-circa 1996 (Box 8, Folder 30)
- Exhibition Files, 1947-circa 1998; Series 4; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 8-9
  Exhibition files are incomplete and contain announcements, photographs and slides, catalogs, notes and correspondence. Files are found for "The Paintings of Dorothy Winslade" (1994), "Hands and Heart, the Art of Healing" (1997), "Annual SFWA Emerging Artists Show" (1988-1994), and "International Women" (1997), among many others. Also found are exhibition lists, price lists, and placards.
  - Exhibition Lists and Price Lists, circa 1980s-1994 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Placards, circa 1980s-circa 1990s (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Annual San Francisco Women Artists, Jurors and Jury Ballots (circa 1947-1966), circa 1947-1956 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "Celebration of International Women" (1991), circa 1991 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "A Woman's Vision" (1992) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "Annual SFWA Emerging Artists Show" (1985-1994), circa 1984-circa 1994 (Box 9, Folder 4-7)
  - "The Paintings of Dorothy Winslade" (1994), 1994-1996 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "SFWA Centennial Show" (1994), 1992-1995 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
  - "We Are All Connected" (1995) (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "SFWA Californina Artists Juried Exhibition" (1995), 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "125th Anniversary San Francisco Art Institute" (1996) (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - "Art of Susan A. Whitney, Exhibit and Silent Auction" (1997), circa 1980-circa 1997 (Box 9, Folder 14-17)
  - "Hands and Heart, the Art of Healing" (1997), circa 1996 (Box 9, Folder 18-19)
  - "International Women" (1997), 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - "Breast Cancer Awareness Art Show" (circa 1998) (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Inventory Records, circa 1974-circa 1985; Series 5; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 9-10
  This series contains artist inventory cards noting artists, some artwork, and some exhibitions.
  Inventory records are arranged in general alphabetical order and grouped to maintain the order in which they were found.
  - A-B, circa 1974-1985 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - B-C, circa 1974-1985 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - C-E, circa 1974-1985 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - F-G, circa 1974-1985 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - G-I, circa 1974-1985 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - J-L, circa 1974-1985 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - M, circa 1974-1985 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - A-E, circa 1974-1985 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - F-K, circa 1974-1985 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Q-S, circa 1974-1985 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - S-T, circa 1974-1985 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - U-W, circa 1974-1985 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - W-Z, circa 1974-1985 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - L-R, circa 1974-1985 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - S-Z, Miscellaneous, circa 1974-1985 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1974-1985 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Drop-Outs and Deceased, circa 1974-1985 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Printed Material, 1926-1999; Series 6; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 10-11, 16
  Printed materials include calendars, clippings, exhibition announcements, brochures and catalogs, general exhibition materials, general printed materials, and two books.
  - Book, The Development of Modern Art in Northern California: Part I, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Book, The Development of Modern Art in Northern California: Part II, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Bulletins, 1926-1999 (Box 10, Folder 10-20)
  - Calendars, San Francisco Women Artists, 1969-1972 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    Oversized calendars housed in Box 16.
  - Clippings, circa 1930s-circa 1996 (Box 10, Folder 22-29)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1970-1996 (Box 10, Folder 30-32)
  - Exhibition Brochures, circa 1975-1989 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Exhibition Brochures, circa 1975-1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1933-1998 (Box 11, Folder 2-9)
  - General Exhibition Materials, circa 1950-circa 1990s (Box 11, Folder 10-15)
  - General Printed Material, circa 1949-1992 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    Oversized material housed in Box 16.
  - Oversized Calendars, San Francisco Women Artists, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Oversized General Printed Material, 1963-1986 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1925-circa 1990s; Series 7; 2.7 Linear feet Boxes 11-13, 15
  Twenty scrapbooks (bound and unbound) contain clippings and exhibition materials, such as announcements, photographs, some notes, and biographies.
  Scrapbooks are arranged in chronological order.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1925-1941 (Box 11, Folder 17-18)
  - Scrapbook 2, circa 1920s-circa 1950s (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook 3, circa 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 20-23)
  - Scrapbook 4, circa 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Scrapbook 4, circa 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook 5, circa 1971-1973 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
  - Scrapbook 6, circa 1971-1973 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 7, circa 1973-1975 (Box 12, Folder 6-8)
  - Scrapbook 8, circa 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 9-10)
  - Scrapbook 9, 1979-1983 (Box 12, Folder 11-15)
  - Scrapbook 10, circa 1983-1985 (Box 12, Folder 16-17)
  - Scrapbook 11, circa 1983-1990 (Box 12, Folder 18-21)
  - Scrapbook 12, circa 1991-1994 (Box 12, Folder 22-23)
  - Scrapbook 13, "Biographies, 100 Years of Women in the Arts", circa 1994 (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
  - Scrapbook 14, circa 1990s (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 15, circa 1990s (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook 16, Exhibitons Scrapbook, circa 1960s-circa 1990s (Box 13, Folder 7-10)
  - Scrapbook 17, Exhibitions Scrapbook, circa 1970s-rirca 1990s (Box 13, Folder 11-12)
  - Scrapbook 18, Exhibitions Scrapbook, circa 1991-1995 (Box 13, Folder 13-15)
  - Oversized Scrapbook 19, circa 1927-1940 (Box 15)
  - Oversized Scrapbook 20, 1977-1978 (Box 15)
- Photographs, circa 1970-circa 1990s; Series 8; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 13-14, 16
  Eight bound and unbound photograph albums, photographs, negatives, and slides depict artwork, exhibitions, galleries, events, artists at work, and images for an exhibition catalog.
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1990s (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Shows, circa 1970s-1992 (Box 13, Folder 17-19)
    Oversized photograph housed in Box 16.
  - Photographs and Negatives for Catalog, circa 1990s (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Slides of Gallery and Receptions, circa 1970-1990 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Slides of SFWA General Meeting, 4-20-97, circa 1997 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Slides of Ming Wu Demo, circa 1996 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Photograph Album 1, Unbound, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 24-27)
  - Photograph Album 2, Unbound, circa 1980s (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Photograph Album 3, Unbound, circa 1987-circa 1989 (Box 14, Folder 3-6)
  - Photograph Album 4, Unbound, Exhibitions, circa 1989 (Box 14, Folder 7-12)
  - Photograph Album 5, Unbound, Exhibitions, 1991-1992 (Box 14, Folder 13-16)
  - Photograph Album 6, Unbound, Exhibitions, circa 1991 (Box 14, Folder 17-20)
  - Oversized Photograph Album 7, Bound, 1996-1998 (Box 16)
  - Oversized Photograph Album 8, Loose Pages, circa 1980s-circa 1990s (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Photograph of Shows, circa 1970s-circa 1990s (Box 16, Folder 3)